2022 has been quite a year and actually
a lot of things sort of slipped my mind
so when I was doing my research I
figured let's go and review 2022
together
in the following way
so I just wanted to go over with all of
you my top stories of 2022 so these are
mainly the ones that I I covered and
then also have a look at some indicators
of what the economy actually did in 2022
so that is real GDP so adjusted for
inflation did we have a good year yes or
no inflation
we had a terrible year pretty clear
than unemployment so these three are the
main variables typically used by
macroeconomists but then because it's
money and macro uh also some
attention for financial markets which
are you know let's just spoil it also
terrible this year
and then finally I thought you know
here's some time for a q a at the end
and uh
yes that's it and with between all of
these steps I I thought Let's uh review
let's do this together so let's review
it together so I want to give a score at
least for the economic indicator so how
let this is a review right so I want to
give it a score and then I'm going to
ask all of you and if I forget let me
know in the chat to say if that's
roughly a good score higher or lower and
also I'm going to be looking at what you
are all saying to get sort of a feel for
the room so we're going to do the review
together so it won't just be me though I
will try to sway your opinion heavily in
my in my favor
so let's uh let's do that how does it
sound so let me just see what people are
saying
thank you for this and nice sweater by
Louis uh thank you I figured this is a
sort of a end of year Christmas type of
thing so you need to wear a Christmas
sweater
uh housing is nuts in Canada is it still
not in Canada because all over the world
it seems to be slowing down but I mean
Canada I know I have some uh some
Canadians in my patreon uh server to
whom I talk regularly and they also keep
going on and on about it and also I've
read this IMF report that sort of with a
slowing housing market Canada New
Zealand Australia these countries that
never had housing bust properly uh are
really really at risk so let's let's
we'll definitely talk about that I think
all right
current situation in China you know
we're definitely going to talk about
China as as well
uh yes let me let's talk about it uh
there it didn't collapse let's put it
like that
um anyhow
okay let's get started
so
top stories of 2022 so I went looking
back to what was I working on start of
the Year 2022
um and actually there was this huge
video on inflation
which in which uh I backed a very
controversial team that is at the time
there was a debate is inflation going to
be transitory so is it is it you know is
it going to be like a little bump and
has it already peaked
kind of thing uh or is it going to be
permanent
now I in I made this massive video I
released it in uh around the start of
January discussing all the arguments
that I that I could find from the
biggest proponents of both teams team
permanent saying uh represented by
people like Peter Schiff who said you
know uh money printing did all of this
we're going to see huge inflation and
gold is going to Skyrocket instead
then there was Jens weitman from the
Deutsche Central Bank German Central
Bank saying hey actually uh the Green
Revolution Energy prices are going to
put uh pressure on inflation from here
on out then we had
um Mr uh what was his name again uh uh
the American treasury secretary X
treasury secretary Larry Summers who
said uh is labor markets are way too hot
we're going to see way more inflation
for longer and then on the other side
there were more Central Bankers Joseph
stiglitz saying you know we can see some
more inflation but it's going to come
down uh some of it came from fiscal
stimulus uh lagar Christine lagar head
of the ECB saying no no it's really
going to be transitory
uh and I made this massive one hour
video and uh I made it actually already
in at the end of November so it was
already outdated uh when I release it
with unlearning economics and we backed
we said okay team transitory has the
best arguments in our opinion and uh
with a condition that the pandemic is
actually over so this was end of
November
2021 and that is right before Delta
became prominent in our minds that is so
that condition was obviously uh for you
know broken but that being said I got a
lot of lack for this uh yeah justifiably
I was one of the economists that didn't
that thought you're gonna inflation
around this time last year had already
peaked it clearly hadn't
what happens uh well the next subject I
I would say
because some of the other uh the other
teams if you notice team members were
also quite wrong right like Peter Schiff
said oh it's money printing but then two
things happened that really undermined
that hypothesis or at least made it
weaker uh one being that the country
that printed the most money the United
States
ended up having uh the strongest
currency the dollar and also less
inflation in Europe where they did far
less of that and then second of course
you had the invasion of Ukraine by
Russia and it as it turned out Putin had
already turned off the gas supply to a
certain extent to Europe and that
reverberated already to to many markets
and this is one of our primary inputs
our house here also runs on gas
um and nobody saw that coming uh it at
least not that I reviewed but let me
know in the chat if you know anyone who
said uh well there must be must have
been someone but I think this is just
um a great lesson in the sense that as a
macroeconomist you can make these
predictions but you are you're dependent
on so many factors including the the
whims of individual people so apparently
the put in I'm not sure how many people
he consulted for this decision
but
yeah as of as the if you want to be the
best macro economic forecaster you
should also be able to to forecast what
individuals that are super influential
like the chairman of the FED may be
somewhat easier to do because they say
what they're going to do but also these
uh world leaders like she if if she is
going to stimulate the economy like
crazy China's economy is not going to
collapse if Russia invades Ukraine
there's going to be a huge extra bout of
energy inflation
which happened so uh that's my excuse
judge me if you please in the chat if
you find that a fair or not excuse
for for being wrong for backing between
team twin story there
um what what do you think it will do now
yeah let's hope that it has actually
peaked now but again now much more
careful because it again depends on what
what happens with energy situation which
is super difficult to to oversee
um so that leads us to the next big
story uh I think the economic War
uh oh but wait let's first see what
people thought about about inflation
from getting roasted or what do you
think
Brad says Putin is the only Economist
suicide coming
exactly yeah
so Jeff your dollars seemed to be the
close analysis uh Navy is saying which
is a reference to this interview I did
with uh Jeff Schneider go check it out
uh on under the live tab on this channel
if you haven't watched it very in-depth
uh although I don't know if he sort of
predicted this kind of inflation one
year ago but that's a good good to check
um
the money supply expands with loans are
created yeah exactly so uh the money is
what Julia is saying so it's not
directly under control of the Central
Bank something that's often forgotten
and that I tried to feature in many of
my videos uh David says here in Sweden
house prices are pretty insane even
after price has gone down about seven or
eight percent they're still super highs
which you're saying I guess and I
totally agree
um I moved from Netherlands to Belgium
at the start of last year and in the
Netherlands house prices were also
extremely crazy in bedroom luckily for
me a bit less so
uh medicine is greater for the Moroccan
economy all right that is interesting as
well I should take a look at that
um
Joseph says uh transfer was the correct
voice in January
yeah yeah that was my opinion
always happy to to hear that of course
but of course also feel free to
criticize me
um
yeah so that that was the inflation
story and it kept going throughout the
year uh it get got way crazy right so I
look back at the numbers it started with
something like five percent in the USA
for three four percent Europe and now
it's 10 Europe 8 USA and in some
countries way crazy but we're gonna talk
about this when we're reviewing the
whole Global inflation situation
economic War so they're also looking
back I made a video
um that was very controversial uh about
Putin's War test so there I made the
case I said at the time it wasn't clear
that they were actually going to invade
but they were threatening to invade and
I said you know uh Putin has amassed has
learned from the the war in 2014 and uh
or the invasion in 2014 of the Crimean
peninsula where they got sanctioned and
they have a massive huge War test of
foreign reserves so that's foreign money
and I said you know you can sanction
them but this is gonna make them immune
uh to to sanctions which was a bit
hyperbolic I have to admit so I let it
change it to shielded against sanctions
because of this huge Reserve War test
and this video was very interesting
because it aged at first really uh badly
and then uh really well in the sense
that the title
you know uh they're immune to to
sanctions well first the ruble
absolutely collapsed
um why because you know I think European
and U.S policy makers had also read the
same sort of economic sources that I do
and saw hey Putin has this huge War test
of foreign reserves if we're going to
sanction the financial sector then he
can say use this to save the banks and
its currency is not going to collapse
because it could just sell these
reserves into the market so that's
selling foreign currency to buy your own
meaning that it won't collapse right
you're buying your own currency back so
they froze the reserves which was
absolutely unheard of absolutely crazy
move uh set like I'm not no legal
scholar but it said a huge huge
precedent in my opinion but uh then uh
put in sort of count countered somewhat
in the sense that he introduced Capital
control so then he was
where the government uh was saying okay
we're going to keep them uh keep foreign
currency in the country we're going to
really restrict how much money can get
out and that had a huge effect then
stabilizing the ruble at first and then
it went up back again
uh because they have had this huge
current account Surplus meaning Trade
Surplus meaning selling lots of oil and
gas for which the price was now higher
uh and so they made more money than ever
which was also uh one of my videos but
and that's only referring to foreign
currency foreign money
uh and so then I made this video like
who's actually winning and at the time
there was huge inflation in Russia
so I gave it to the west but after that
um massive energy inflation especially
in Europe but also in many more
countries contributing to Sky High
inflation
Russian inflation went down quite a bit
more but still really high and then
the Russian economy also stabilized but
still
and we're going to look at this a little
bit later as well am I looking at GDP
their economy shrank real GDP by four
percent whereas Western economies or
Allied economies I should say because
Japan and South Korea Singapore also
sanctioned
grew quite a bit more even sort of
accounting for inflation so I think that
analysis as
still still stands but you know this was
super painful for all sides huge
Economic Development right after a huge
pandemic so yeah
I can understand uh why
these videos were so popular and also
why people are voting that this was
actually a really bad economic year
um final lesson I would say from the
sanctions is that the the Imp the export
import sanctions of real Goods seem to
be hurting way more than the ex
Financial sanctions so remember uh back
in March oh all the Russian banks are
going to be cut off Swift that was all
over the news
seemingly didn't do so much right but
you saw all of these tanks and airplanes
or airplanes flying with a cheap
consumer grade GPS's
and all inside of that was all sort of
Western Equipment uh
I've also read quite a few reports at
industry in Russia is struggling they've
really scaled back to much more inferior
technology so that export sanctions seem
to be the ones doing the damage whereas
the financial sanctions
seem not to be so impactful against a
current account Surplus country which is
Russia which gets its foreign currency
which gets so much foreign currency that
it can
save its own financial sector I would
say that that would be lesson for me but
I'm wondering what uh what do you think
about this
and I want to do an update on all of
this early next year maybe I figured
maybe it could be nice or good idea to
do this one year after or so
let me see what people are saying uh
um just economy going is not enough
what what do you think about the economy
that Terrors on goods from China are
contributing to inflation
um yeah probably they are
but I'm not uh I'm not entirely sure if
if this is a super big factor at the
moment because energy is is just such a
big factor at the moment
all right then let's move on so that was
in my opinion second base story but also
let me know if you think uh there are
big stories that I'm I'm forgetting
China slow down uh this was already
at the end of 2021 a story ever Grande
is going out of business yes or no
property sector slowing down you have
this huge huge ghost cities cities that
have been built and nobody's living in
them at some point there were reports
yeah but they're gonna move in there and
and seemingly
uh to some cities you know this actually
happened but then others not it's quite
difficult to get information
accurate information from inside China
about this I would say
but uh I think most economists agreed
that the property bubble was so so
insane in China given that they had
property prices on Western levels
whereas
incomes are not on those levels right so
that's hugely expensive relative to
income property I know some some of you
talk about it property bubble in Canada
but
the Chinese property bubble is
or was super big but then the government
itself tried to deflate it so they tried
to tighten the screws make the rules
tougher for credit flowing to to these
uh to these developers that were making
so many properties that nobody was
seemingly living in and yeah so I think
economists have been saying for a super
long time now or many and many investors
as well that China's economy is due for
a reckoning their debt to GDP is rising
because they're spending or making
creating all of this credit to do
something that's not really contributing
to GDP as much it is of course
contributing to GDP
the property sector is a profit is has
been estimated to be 27 of of um
of the economy in China because of
course construction workers are still
working they're still buying food
they're they're still buying materials
that it that does contribute to GDP and
that is roughly
hasn't been seen that that often before
only in Spain right before 2008 and
Spain had this huge property bubble so
this is why I think the most reputable
Economist on China that I follow have
been comparing it to Japan which also
had this huge property bubble right
before uh its economy completely
stagnated and therefore I made a call I
like this is probably going to stagnate
then of course back in 2021 at start
they were the big coveted winners they
did the serial covet policy was
seemingly very successful not that many
cases
but now uh or during 2022 that
completely changed
and the economy really started to hurt
because they had to lock down so many
times with Omicron variant which is much
more transmissible uh and so this I
think is when many many people became
super in investment terms I would say uh
bearish negative about China and for me
this sort of really sort of culminated
in YouTube videos uh proclaiming the
collapse of China in 30 days uh and this
was it when was it September so uh that
didn't happen and these these videos got
millions of views super popular and
they're just annoyed annoyed me because
yeah come on uh
but so I made the response video anyway
that's the that's the thumbnail that you
see there and I think uh there I argued
no yes it's a big problem but they they
have their own currency they like Russia
current account Surplus country so
they're not so they have some wiggle
room it's not always good to have a
current account Surplus but it gives you
in these situations some wiggle room
because you you're not at risk of
running out of foreign currency your own
currency you can always create but
you're not running at a risk it's really
risky like Sri Lanka had to run out of
foreign currency and then your own
currency collapses and then you get
massive inflation so uh that was my
argument and I think that actually held
up fairly well and I also said you know
they're going to slow down a lot and
seemingly that that's now also the case
but they've now abandoned their covet 19
uh zero lockdowns strategy and so we
might see somewhat of a Resurgence
although the
property sector bubble could definitely
be a huge downward force that that may
be much bigger but it's very difficult
to to actually say
but that being said this story
definitely dominated 2021 I would say
also because it meant for all sorts of
other countries to whom China was
Landing a lot especially in the Belton
Road initiative in the Asian countries
around China
that this money was now you know not
flowing anymore so quickly so
and this contributed arguably to some
other crises like we saw in Pakistan and
Sri Lanka
on top of of course the economic War so
on top of that all of these countries
had to deal with Sky High Energy prices
Sky High food prices and now also with
less investment from China less demand
from China for raw materials which
plummeted in price so huge story I would
say
I wonder what what you all think about
this the China story I don't think we've
seen the last of it
what do you think
Mr Wolf has an opinion about
Norway uh
we'll get to that
I don't say too much internet yet let's
see
let's see all right let's move on then
to what in my opinion is uh
Sri Lanka they oh okay okay this is good
uh CC says Sri Lanka they owe the most
adapt to the west and that's true right
even though a lot of the deaths from
China were hidden
they still owe most depth to to wet the
West right and this is why in my Sri
Lanka video I said okay there's multiple
factors I made sort of a game out of it
like who who's the worst but
that's YouTube has to be a bit
entertaining uh but uh even though it's
a very serious situation
but of course
yes you can borrow most from someone but
if one source of borrowing dries up
you're still going to be in a lot of
trouble right so it doesn't matter too
much that and I'm not blaming China for
this right it's like China's economy is
slowing down they don't want to do that
and so this is why a lot of that their
loans are now also drying up and and
this hurts a lot of economies but I
don't think you can blame the vat on
China you could you could blame on them
that they have been lending to the wrong
project that they have been lending to
corrupt projects and therefore it
doesn't contribute to an economy
building up therefore they cannot repay
it
but you cannot really blame them for
having a slowing economy and then not
being able to land so much right
all right uh China's too complicated for
my brain yes
[Music]
that's that's true uh yeah I'm gonna
dive into it a little bit more in 2023
how many more defaults do you do you see
in the third world many more uh in fact
Ghana just the defaulted
and they uh they apparently did it
prematurely so they didn't have to is
the the last thing that I
read about it but um you know this storm
that Sri Lanka was in which was the next
uh great story uh on my on my slides uh
is it's the same for everyone and
especially so this is I think the
the the next stories let's go to the
currency crisis and what I found is
particularly noteworthy is that there
there is this pattern of current account
deficit countries so trade deficit
countries getting into trouble notably
Sri Lanka but then there's also uh
Tunisia uh who hasn't defaulted yet but
was was getting in trouble uh Haiti is
terrible at the moment as it has huge um
as a huge crisis it's not being covered
so much
at the moment but it's on my radar and
many countries in Africa Ghana is now
the the one most in the news
but I think there are many countries
that are really in a in a tricky
situation Pakistan is another big one
that I didn't get to cover but and then
they also had huge floods but all of
these countries you see all major
Emerging Markets
are or maybe maybe most economies have a
lot of problems at the moment but the
ones with the the biggest current
account deficits seem to get into the
most trouble simply because their
currencies then started collapsing
because there's not enough demand for
them because they're importing way more
needing to pay their own currency
um and then you get way more inflation
right and so you're basically running
out of foreign money and you cannot
import the stuff that you really need
like fuel what you saw in Sri Lanka as
well these huge queues for for gas and
these are the countries that have had a
really tough time and economists call
this
phenomena that you have this huge
difference between current account
Surplus and current account deficit
countries
Global imbalances is what they call this
and and these are and this was a really
hot topic right before the global
financial crisis
um where the oil exporters were having
these huge current gun surpluses and
China
but this lesson a little bit and now
it's totally back and you you're going
to see this as well we're going to talk
about inflation Growth Oil exporters
um you know are on top of the world
and the ones that who had this chronic
on deficit are really struggling and one
of them notably has been the UK the UK
uh it's one of the identical further
from the currency crisis this is the one
I covered I didn't cover I was just
working on other videos but there they
were this is not a coincidence they had
a nine or eight percent current account
deficit and the pound crashed when the
government announced look we're gonna do
this tax because
for wealthy people that
import a lot of stuff
so yeah
all right currency crisis we haven't
seen the last of it but I'm definitely
going to cover that more next year as
well sadly because this is not not a
happy thing
um
let's see some of the comments
[Music]
the bank of Japan a new
um
new curve control uh I I still have to
read up on it a bit more carefully
for commenting on that could Saudi
Arabia abandon the U.S dollar system so
this is what summer militia
what a name uh says yes they well
It's tricky because the dollar is just
so dominant that's also really useful
for Saudi Arabia because I I think they
buy also their stuff typically mostly
with the US dollar but they have been
talking to China to
start trading in huon as well and one
thing that we have been seeing perhaps
is at least a strong will of countries
like China Russia and their allies to
move away from the dollar system but
yeah it's really difficult but if you
know let's let's put it like this if you
want to do that if you want to move away
from the dollar system
which does allow the United States to
run a super high current account deficit
then Saudi Arabia has a good country to
get on your side especially now with
these high oil prices
so that's what I would would say to that
am I parsing the chapters too fast uh
cuckoo I'm sorry I will try to slow down
a little bit but there's so much more
uh
yeah
all right let's continue currency crisis
uh because all of this so I just wanted
to give you an overview of the biggest
stories in my opinion of 2021 for the
global economy all of this is going to
come back when we talk about GDP
inflation and unemployment again and
then there's also a q a at the end so
don't worry uh I'll Stick Around
next biggest story in my opinion cost of
living crisis so uh this also I would
say
why you have this difference between
pretty high GDP growth numbers
so and yet and and low unemployment
which we're also going to come to
and yet
the people feel as if we're already in
the recession as if the times are
already really bad why because for most
working people I would say who have a
steady job
the cost of living has really gone up so
their salary is not keeping up with
their main costs which are energy and I
can confirm that our Energy bill has
absolutely gone through the roof we had
to be much more careful with our energy
usage which is maybe the bright side
but also food prices
um and and that's
and that's even more terrible for the
people who can afford at least because
you know you need you need some element
of energy
you need at least food and food is a
bigger part of your expenses if you're
for most poor people typically like the
how the rich you are typically the more
relatively you spend on other stuff so
so if food prices go through the roof
yeah it really hurts you the less you
have and this it hurts most people and
that's I think is why so many of you
voted uh 2022 was a good year for the
macroeconomy
no it was not 82 says it was not a good
year
so yeah
that uh is the cost of living crisis
very acute in Europe and this video I
did saying hey how much worse is going
to get so far so good uh in Europe at
least is because we had this very mild
weather so I talked about these
different scenarios saying you know you
have the mild recessing scenario a bad
recession and an apocalyptic recession
depending on the weather what Putin will
do next uh how fast we can move to
alternative energy sources and so far in
Europe
um even though uh energy price is still
way too high uh the weather was amazing
except for last week when it was super
cold and that has a huge impact on
demand but then even even taking that
into account demand was reduced in in
countries like here in Belgium by 20
percent
purely because people were saving uh
energy usage
um or maybe buying solar panels but also
just turning the heat down I turned it
down here from
normally 20 to 18 uh degrees a Celsius
that is
and actually you know if you wear a
Christmas sweater
uh to me that's not a big big problem uh
I would say and it saves a ton of energy
and I was also talking to
um my research intern here Oscar who uh
is German and had these contacts in the
German industry who would say you know
uh German industry cut back a lot and
then some economists would say yeah
that's super negative because that means
they're not producing so much anymore
and then he said well anecdotally some
of these factories were just going uh
you know have a careful look at their
production process and they saw all of
these uh big inefficiencies you know
burning the the the furnace way too high
it's not necessary and I think for many
households it was similar you can but
you can buy this little uh pillow uh put
it under the door so that it doesn't
um that doesn't come so much wind
through it right and I think a lot of of
that also happened uh cold showers uh
way you know shorter showers 20 demand
reduction so these two elements that I
talked about in that video Europe's
upcoming recession
so far seem to have really uh helped at
least
so
um
okay kindness lupus thank you so much
for supporting Channel first of all and
you're saying but what about Germany
cost of living here is rocketing now
this this is still true right uh it here
in Belgium as well the cost of living is
still Sky High going up depending a
little bit on if you had if you have to
reveal your energy contract
um this is inflation right this is the
still I'm not uh saying this is not
another big problem
uh it's it's still the case it was just
that we expected three months ago for it
to be so much worse even still because
of energy
uh but it's uh it's still a problem okay
this is interesting uh okay this is
difficult name to pronounce but y p e y
one says if the Germans are inefficient
I'm starting to worry look let me tell
you something controversial uh being a
Dutchman and this kind of lamb in hot
Waters Germany is not so efficient
okay they have the reputation for being
super efficient uh but it could be a lot
more efficient
um in my humble opinion
uh conversion opinion of that I'm not
going to explain it too much more people
please defend Germany in the chat
against such an outrageous claim
but coming from the Netherlands I would
say
not as efficient as I had expected
room for improvement and they're
improving right so that's good
okay
so these are in my opinion the biggest
stories of the global economy in 2022
inflation
the economic War China slowdown currency
crises in many countries including the
United Kingdom and the huge cost of
living crisis in many many countries
prominently also in Europe
yes
Germans
Raul agrees with me uh
some people are saying that this is
exactly what a German would say and it
could be true
all right uh let's see
so I'm also going to talk about how much
these themes will likely work into next
year but uh we're gonna get to that
let's first now start with uh oh I just
wanted to mention and there's a shout
out to the plain bagel great uh Channel
if you're into Finance he also talks
about economy sometimes the biggest
story I miss I really said about it I
prepared the whole video or I prepared a
lot of research for it
the crash of the bound they managed to
stabilize it so far but I was just
working on too many videos at the time
to cover it
I think what had been said about it is
that they had this current account
deficit it was very stupid moved then to
tax cuts for the rich and they also I
think uh spent a lot of money on making
the energy prices lower and that the
controversial thing about that is you
know that that does help people but then
they also don't reduce their demand so
much and your problem that energy prices
are still Sky High is still there and
it's just more difficult if you have a
current account deficit
I would like to add to that that the UK
has had this business model for a long
time or economic model
where they wanted to be the banker of
the world London is still as big of a
financial center as
New York whereas the UK is no longer the
global superpower that it was back
uh you know in the 30s right
strange so what they did is they courted
Europeans London is your Europe's
Banking Center and they quoted a lot of
let's say
less Democratic rulers and Elites from
less wealthy countries put it like this
that's why they say London is is London
grad and you have all of this Russian
money there
now what's happening uh first with
brexit they make their banking center
and they're there for their currency
much less attractive to the Europeans
okay which is you know they had their
reasons but
that doesn't help the pound uh as as a
major investment destination then they
now they have these sanctions which you
know is uh
makes makes a lot of sense politically
speaking but what can it makes sense
then that the consequence is that a lot
of Russian money is being pulled out of
London because it's no longer the safe
haven then maybe a lot of other similar
type money is also going to think twice
about putting all of that in the UK and
that might be a good thing
but
it also just makes the pound less
attractive it decreases the demand for
the pound and so I think it makes sense
that if you look at the
the exchange rate of the pundit has been
falling for for years now for 10 years
like if you zoom out if you cut through
the noise a little bit you'll see that
this latest collapse is just that it's
this latest collapse it's not oh
listro's collapse the bound and that's
the whole story no I think there's more
to it I think their economic model the
source of demand for pounds is under
pressure and that's why I want to make a
video about
still in my archive
maybe it will come out next year
depending on what happens with the with
the brown
so that's a little preview and that's
the biggest story I missed and if you
want to get the details more on the
financial side shout outs to the plain
bagel and also Patrick Boyle who covered
this story from the financial
perspective really well
I would say
[Music]
um
all right some chats about this
uh okay lots of cheddar uh
Harry says UK is a bigger better
developed version of Lebanon there is
actually a little bit of Truth there is
right in the sense that Lebanon was the
preeminent financial center of the
Middle East it was this stable Safe
Haven uh which now has shifted to Dubai
and Lebanon uh yeah has terrible economy
at the moment I wouldn't say it's like
that bad I know there's still a lot of
amazing research there's a lot of still
amazing fundamentals also in the UK but
um I get where you're coming from with
that when you say that
uh okay so this is uh kabil Yuri maybe
you should do Pakistan before next year
to give the rest of hope it can't get
worse than here
um yeah and that's uh sadly uh I know
this is uh this is the case in the sense
that there has been these huge floods in
Pakistan as well uh
yeah their economy is terrible at the
moment
um
I would like to cover it uh although
let's put it like this I hope I I hope
it don't wasn't will not get worse and
then I don't have to cover it
um so best of luck there
all right so we get to the reviewing
part of the uh
of the session let's review
the global economy so this is not your
own economy this is the global economy
because I cannot review all economies in
the world
2021 a real GDP so this chart from the
World Bank the global economy is in
steep slow down the blue line was uh
sort of the projected line uh you know
before covet
red line up to where you see these
diverging lines is where
we are now so we have seen real economic
growth uh even though there's miscayo
inflation and that makes sense right in
the sense that the economy took such a
beating in 2020 you know these and and
partially in 2021 still all of these
lockdowns come on that that had to have
had a serious effect this was absolutely
massive I think economists at least or
people talking about economies should
appreciate more how big this uh this
shock is how you would say than
economics was so so big
um and you know we have recovered from
it but we're
we're below our our path that we were on
is so this is how you should read this
graph and then the World Bank makes this
sort of scenario analysis saying oh you
know Baseline we keep growing like this
but we're never returning according to
them to to that previous path so this
lasting damage from the pandemic makes
sense
um but it could could even be a bit
worse
so real GDP uh has grown so we're going
to review it right so please get ready
to give this some some marks some scale
of let's use a scale of
one to ten shall we do that scale of one
to ten
um 10 being good uh is perfect one being
ex the worst ever uh maybe uh something
I think the worst economic collapse has
been uh in countries like Ukraine
uh Libya Pakistan Haiti Sri Lanka that
that would be maybe like uh a three just
to give some
some perspective on how to create this
anyway uh yes it's not it's it's been
Stellar growth has been fairly high but
nothing spectacular also if you look at
the trend that it was on previously
fairly similar and it doesn't seem to be
that we're catching up so also makes
sense that people aren't are pessimistic
about this right
then uh winners and losers so had a look
at some countries that extremely well or
not so well uh Saudi Arabia big winner
of uh 20 20 lit up 2022 when we look at
real GDP
plus a real GPA so correct for inflation
plus 9.8 percent is from one of my
sources if you're gonna google you might
find slightly different numbers
depending on the source here I used uh
the oec oecd yeah for this one India 6.6
also surprising uh surprisingly high in
list India did actually really well this
year
could also be that they had a bad year
last year's which you always should give
into account but uh Saudi Arabia for
obvious reasons right oil prices through
the roof what were the winners Qatar
Norway Saudi Arabia
you United Arab Emirates including Dubai
but losers
Ukraine
makes sense I would say but still Let's
uh just look in horror at this number
minus 35
GDP real GDP growth for Ukraine
makes sense uh but then surprising to me
Libya minus 18.5 percent
and that's strange because Libya's main
export is oil so you could have expected
things to improve there
I looked into it it was a bit difficult
to find what uh the most convincing
reason I could find is that the security
situation there is really bad again so
maybe not maybe not I'm not sure if
anyone in the chat is there or has super
as much pure political knowledge there
but maybe not full official Civil War
but still a high sort of disorder chaos
um some other countries did Super poorly
I couldn't find their numbers here in
the OCD database but Sri Lanka Haiti
Afghanistan as well covered it in a
video Pakistan terrible some of these
were highly inflationary Afghanistan not
so inflationary but because
strange story they outsourced their
money printer and then that was
sanctioned and so they actually couldn't
make any more money there and the
banking system the private bank system
was also
at odds with uh Sharia law so you know
not functioning properly after Taliban
took over so that there you might see
money printing can be a factor for sure
so they had deflationary or or still
inflationary if I remember correctly but
not as high as Sri Lanka Pakistan Haiti
Russia still minus 3.9 so yes
they did much better than expected after
the first sanctions hit but come on
that's still really bad like if that was
real GDP growth in the United States uh
I think or you had way more Doom videos
on YouTube than you had now
so
um
yeah though I'm just gonna give an
overview that's the idea here
so what would you say sort of given this
like okay we had a fair GDP growth
um
like overall right but we didn't catch
up and that's a real shame after ideally
after lockdowns all over the world the
economy should bounce back to where it
was right that that's what you you would
hope that didn't happen lasting lasting
impact
what would you score it a scale of one
to ten
one being worst 10 being perfect
um
three being
countries that like Libya
Ukraine okay so so uh just let me know
in the chat
I am uh leaning towards
because we're not talking about
inflation yet I'm leaning towards A6 out
of 10. that's my opinion so uh let me
know what you think and then I I can
adjust it a little bit
April April says 4 out of ten
I do like six
the name is I do like and he says six I
do like six okay
uh let me see if I can actually
I can end the poll six six five five uh
seven
all right seven
okay what I'm gonna do is like I'm gonna
say
7 is too high this is the pool going to
be
because I see some let me know uh please
vote do vote quickly
because I see it most answers around
seven uh and then uh sixes fives I
haven't seen so many
nobody's going above me yes it's too
high 70 says too high
5.5 out of 10 by Juan adjusting from a
six but maybe that's a rounding error
so yeah okay 75 thinking it's too high
okay seven was my base uh six was my
oh wait I said six and now I'm saying
seven is too high is a question well
okay
what is this yeah I see some sevens okay
seven is too high then that was my bet
for asking the wrong question but then
let's say it's a six is what I'm getting
from from all of you so that was fairly
important six real GDP
review of the global economy okay
that's real GDP but now to the real
story uh really beat a real story
inflation this this let's let's just say
like this 2022 was the year of inflation
the year that inflation came back
um so what you see here is a map of uh
the World by the IMF uh colors
indicating the sort of orangey is is
high inflation the more orange you get
the higher your inflation is The Greener
you get you get low inflation and green
inflation in their opinion is roughly
around the target of two percent right
so China
roughly around two percent
Saudi Arabia there we have them again uh
and then yeah I just wanted to show you
this chart in the bottom left corner
which is uh coal and gas gold oil prices
and this is it goes back a long time and
I think you can see here that the shock
we've seen here is is almost equivalent
to what we saw in uh the 80s great oil
crisis
that that had a huge and lasting impact
on the economics profession and that was
also the maybe coincidentally the last
time that we saw this this massive
inflation
so I think that was definitely the
biggest Factor another uh key uh point
of evidence that I I you know I've seen
for that is that at the start of the
year it was all about U.S inflation and
now it's all about European inflation
who uh was closest to
um the Russian gas and had the most
energy inflation Europe
so that I don't think many people will
disagree with that anymore
but
um
some positive news that's the second
chart that is global Shipping rate so at
the start of 2022 everybody was like oh
people are locked down inside they're
ordering all their stuff from China and
not going to a bar anymore that trend
has reversed and so
uh it seems to be that Global Supply
chains are going back to normal uh
Freight rate so that means like how
expensive it is to send a package from
one portal to another via ship is really
now coming down so there are a lot of
um
uh sort of goods Services goods mainly
that contribute to inflation last year
that have gone down significantly which
is hopeful but I'm not gonna
yeah uh might be still overpowered by
another energy increase right so let's
see
who winners and losers uh winners had
low inflation in this case that's why
you see them there so Japan
1.99 inflation there I've seen some
other sources three percent but this one
I found China 2.2 Saudi Arabia 2.9 and
also interestingly Switzerland
three percent inflation
strange right uh maybe my hypothesis was
wrong Switzerland's also in the middle
of Europe they should also have Sky
inflation if it was Russian energy right
Japan also uh Imports a lot of uh energy
also from Russia so
China doesn't but China so for China
there's the the economy seems to be
slowing down so much that demands so low
that
uh yeah that this has contributed to
them having very low inflation Saudi
Arabia is maybe selling uh oil cheaper
in the country and uh is is uh using its
uh its massive gains from from all of
that oil
to uh to to compensate uh partially the
population
so Switzerland and Japan Mysteries I
looked into it a little bit uh what I
found is that
Switzerland uh had there's a couple of
factors the
Swiss currency went up like crazy making
All Imports uh cheaper because uh likely
because the Central Bank raised interest
rates and maybe because it's a safe
haven in Europe typically
uh maybe especially with with what was
going on in the UK not entirely sure but
um their currency went up a lot
so that contributed if your currency
gets uh worth way more All Imports
including energy is cheaper right
another thing
they're really relying on um
a lot of renewable energy apparently
hydropower
on top of that they had some price
controls uh more than other European
countries in the article that I read at
least and Japan also apparently has
quite a lot of price controls on
energy and wheat especially meaning that
producers cannot
cannot hike their prices so much they
have to do it in small steps so if you
have that then you know you likely have
lesser less inflation but you might
expect that a lot of your producers will
get in trouble but yeah
these are the best explanations that I
could find for these strange cases so to
see I mean if you look at the world map
everybody had huge inflation
uh so here I see uh into Europe in the
chat uh super nice to see you uh Hugo
from into Europe who's also been using
the studio here from time time and who
has made a lot of animations for me uh
last year so if people uh didn't notice
maybe my animations got a bit nicer
because uh Hugo has been helping me out
from into Europe with with that so huge
shout out to into Europe and thank you
for it for joining the chat and thank
you for contributing and saying yeah the
there's not so much natural gas usage in
Switzerland
Oliver thank you so much uh for uh
contributing to the channel and he says
Japan is taking to zero percent interest
rates which helps to create a deflation
um yeah I wonder but there uh arguably
that also uh led to this collapse in the
Yen which should have
uh increased in uh inflation right if
their currency is going down so hmm
yeah
all right uh
yeah Buxton P says that the DNS lost a
lot right so yeah that's uh that's it's
a mystery maybe actually I should once
again return to Japan next year with a
more continued analysis but let's see
okay let's go to losers uh of this year
uh not talked about so much in the news
still the biggest losers like absolutely
crazy inflation 200 percent uh and one
for Venezuela I think
Sudan also 180 or something something
like that very high numbers
these are just countries that are in um
in sort of a collapsing state right like
the their their huge government failure
the currency that the government issues
typically if you this is something when
I did these inflation videos on
hyperinflation all of that always most
countries that have hyperinflation
either have huge current account deficit
so uh their currency then collapses
because they try to import they have to
import so much uh and they they bring
their own money to the to the Foreign
Exchange Market nobody wants it so the
value goes down second case is uh when a
government collapses uh a currency is a
liability
is that from the government from the
central bank if a government collapses
it's absolutely worthless it can no
longer enforce you to use that currency
I think this is uh and they might also
be printing money that's that that could
also definitely be true but definitely
often happens as a reaction to either of
these two things because then either the
choices don't pay any wages anymore or
print the money and the print money is
less painful at that moment but
you know the real problem is this insane
current account deficit or a collapsing
government
uh so either you just go down in a huge
deflationary spiral or or hyperinflation
sadly Sudan and Venezuela
getting close to that uh also less
talked about this year Argentino
number I found to 72 percent I also
found somewhere that they're getting
close now to 90 percent so maybe I
should do a video about that next year
they have a highly dollarized economy
which is the same as turkey and turkey
also has a super high inflation
this was covered quite well I also made
a video about it
most people were saying it's interest
rates
uh I think it contributed for sure but
hugely dollarized economy what has the
government done they have now
implemented this new policy called a
literaryation instead of dollarization
liraisation and that actually seemed to
have worked a little bit because the
Lira has now stabilized a little bit
after a super long fall
but they also use some other tricks and
that is what my next video will be about
which I think I will likely release on
Thursday so in two days so that's that
will be the final video for
um for this year for money macro
then also big loser on the inflation
front Eastern Europe especially the
baltics uh that were super Reliant the
more you really see this pattern the
more Reliant you were in Russian gas the
higher your inflation is now
have I missed any winners or losers in
your opinion let me know and otherwise I
think we're gonna go to vote here uh
what is uh the score for
the global economy regarding inflation
again
well actually let's say that here's uh
Sudan and Venezuela score a uh one just
to say like how bad hyperinflation
actually really is so that's the the the
one
um let's give uh Japan in this case
let's give them a um a nine two percent
inflation
in this environment uh is great right
like they they were they wanted a little
bit of inflation they have two percent
inflation their target
so Japan is a nine
Venezuela is a one what is the global
economy in in your opinion
let me know in the comments so that I
can get a bit of an idea
just gonna close that pool previous poll
[Music]
um
okay it's trans story then
all right
so I would uh five okay from uh
correctly Harry says
3.535 if you want better Marie no before
okay I've broken five summer malicious
six still actually not so bad okay okay
here they're they're coming 4.5 Japan is
a nine yeah that's good four five five
four four five yeah this is uh
definitely worse than the GDP score
so I would uh agree with uh this
[Music]
okay
five I think I would also would would
have been the thing that came to mind
for me
so five out of ten is what I would say
because
um
because uh Venezuela's the one you know
globally they're still
um
I I might um
go even a bit lower otherwise but okay
I'm gonna say let's start a ball
so is uh so I think five is on the high
side
but might be correct so I would say is
is a five two high for Global inflation
score that my question to you is it too
high so
if many people vote Yes it's too high
and then we're going to lower it to four
I'd say
so you should Now by now see this poll
uh yes no and no vote
so let's see global inflation terrible
year and then we can move on to happier
news after this
yes
five Daniel says five feels like a very
average year this year has been really
bad here for the economy four is the
best case
I would say like uh the the what I
typically use in a one to ten score
let's say for grading students is a six
is sufficient
a seven is like what you average
uh
vote no please is
people are saying this actually close
call 54 says uh
I think no 55 okay I'm gonna end it
and then see what the result was
um okay no it's not too high so we're
gonna stay with a 5 54 so inflation
2022 a five a place in 2020.
final so now we have a six for real GDP
there we go five for inflation and
next up unemployment
so let's talk about unemployment because
I think with all the Doom and Gloom uh
this hasn't been talked about enough
and it's also something that
um you might not talk about
enough because most people in most
countries are employed
right so uh for most people even though
they read about this in the paper and
this is not such a big issue even if
there is high unemployment although I've
lived in South Africa for a while
you do notice uh I I would say that you
would not sit on the street you feel
inequality is not a nice feeling I I
would say but for most people who are
employed this is perhaps less top of
mind but I would argue it's very
important and especially youth
unemployment because if you have youth
unemployment for a long time you get
this really disillusioned young people
especially men higher crime
and also they don't get a chance to
develop right it takes time you need a
job like anyone if you've had a job in
10 years or maybe you've had a job for
10 years you get better at it right if
you don't have a job ever you never get
better at it so for an economy super
important
I think a bit underrated unemployment
so let's look at these graphs so I try
to highlight some countries uh it has
been trending down for most countries
unemployment is fairly low
and this might have contributed to
inflation
but let's let's celebrate this and also
let's have a look at countries like
Spain and Greece these are the top two
lines in the chart who've seen their
employment unemployment rates go from in
the 20s to in the High Teens so 12 13
which is still absolutely way too high
okay let's just be clear about that but
still
there's finally something positive to
say here positive trend
however then two points I want to make
about this
uh one is youth unemployment so China
was in the news now that youth
unemployment was actually going up quite
a bit up to 20 which is precisely what I
was talking about is so bad it's one of
the worst forms of uh unemployment
uh and okay
this is a headline from The Economist in
developing countries many
many people cannot afford not to work
meaning that uh the the because I looked
at statistics and southern Europe is
always super bad South Africa as well
and then uh southeast Asia for example
some very poor countries very low
unemployment numbers so I found it quite
strange but apparently what happens
there is that people often don't
register for unemployment benefits
because this is so so poorly organized
that it's more of a hassle or it costs
money or or effort or money right
instead of hustling on the street to
register so okay the statistics uh are
not as accurate for the whole world
for this but uh
still a downward Trend at least in
advanced economies
uh let's let's have some positive news
as well
uh winners so advanced economies on
average down to four and a half percent
from 6.6 or something last year which is
great
Spain agrees like I mentioned and the
rest of southern Europe uh winners
notably in this category even though
it's still really bad unemployment so
nothing to celebrate 13 unemployment but
if you're used to 20 that's much better
and I also read some economic
commentators talking about how great it
is that now the economies are open again
the tourists are going back to southern
Europe which is great for these
economies
uh some losers South Africa uh I had a
look at that their unemployment rate the
trend is absolutely very worrying 34
unemployment and that it it's like this
line that's only going up it's not going
up uh
straight up but it's it's only it's a
trend rather than what you see here the
world trend is downwards South Africa
trend is upwards and they and 34
employment I mean that's that's crazy uh
I lived in South Africa you can see this
industry you can definitely see it it's
really terrible so
the losers in this regard given that the
data for many countries because maybe
there are many African countries that
have this problem but it doesn't show up
in the data
youth unemployment also important to
talk about China is a loser in that
regard this year I would say you also
have there this this has been the news
quite a bit this trend that uh you know
lying flat is what they call it that
people young people are getting so
desperate to get a job
um that situation here has really in in
Europe has really disappeared a little
bit 10 years ago
and that's quite remarkable because 10
years ago or something it was much more
difficult for people like my students I
was the instrument to get to find a job
and now my students are are having no
trouble finding a job so
still Sky inflating inflation is eating
away at their wage but at least they
have a job
okay maybe nice have some good news as
well but maybe I'm being too optimistic
uh let me know if that's true
Thompson's EU is a loser in general or
Unemployment uh on this the trend is
good right but unemployment in the EU is
is much too uh
it's much too high that's true I agree
so uh what would you say unemployment
development in 2022 global economy
great
hi lo
let me know
South Africa
I would say
is a three
and uh which country has super low
unemployment
Germany still have super low
I think so Netherlands still yeah really
low unemployment in the Netherlands at
the moment I think uh Singapore yeah
let's uh say these kind of countries get
a nine
so what is Switzerland is normally not
considered uh on shoe Mount part of
southern Europe no
no
um okay
I do like says 7.5 Dell season 8
Alexander says a seven
uh I would say
say a little bit High
and eight
um so here zerumo says yeah it's weird
for me someone who graded out of the 08
crisis which was me as well
uh where there were no jobs and a bunch
of us had to do schooling or sit board
yeah exactly so that
that's not talked about enough right
that this situation has actually changed
I would say
889 from Lee uh
someone says Europe is good but still
gives it a 10. so okay uh seven seven so
I would I'm gravitating towards an eight
for unemployment
uh uh let's say I don't see too many
people going above that
so let's see if you think that is too
high
uh is
an eight
too high
for an employee and
globally 2022.
let's do pull
associate seven eight
so here's zerumo says what's worse
erosion of their weight in the inflation
plus housing bubbles or now what we're
having jobs
no clue if it's better or worse for
Zoomers versus Millennials with a
10-year different
yeah so this is uh something I talked
about uh with some other economists
during the year that what you see is uh
that
in voters when you look at voters uh
inflation seems to be a much more hated
than a recession maybe even like people
get really well yeah depending on how
heavy the recession is but anyway that
was the hypothesis was there was that
inflation hits all of us whereas
unemployment Only Hits a few of us and
when you look at you live in a democracy
then that you know there there's there's
likely to be a bias towards a hate for
inflation
that was hypothesis maybe it's not true
but uh I thought it was still an
interesting I hadn't thought about it
like that uh beforehand
what does to my high mean uh big boss
Big Boss uh it means uh like oh an eight
is too high of a number so uh you know
rather unemployment
2022 should get a seven or a six or a
five or something like that
okay let's see
well let's end the poll
and say what do we have uh is it too
high
uh no says so say most people so it's
not too high so okay again let's just
gonna stick with an eight
so Unemployment uh gets an eight
inflation A5 and oops GDP is six so it
wasn't a bad year for the economy
um
most people say yes but uh
the the grades aren't are not so so
insanely bad uh X-Men says he cannot see
the ball I'm sorry
uh I do not know how to fix this at the
moment
final thing final Point global economy
2022 we've done the grading so far is
financial markets uh this is not macro
there's a this is money macro to a
channel right so money macro we talk
about
not just financial markets but
money monetary policy inflation that
kind of stuff and also sometimes
financial markets
so but we do when we talk about money we
do often talk about gold uh Bitcoin you
know are they actually the inflation
hedge are they the real types of money
uh some people uh like to argue
well
top chart here uh also possibly because
why many people think it was terrible
here financial markets had a terrible
year uh the the above two indexes are
the global
mcsi if I pronounce correctly indexes
uh this is a long chart so this is over
a long period of time but the little uh
sort of uh you know downward uh
correction you could say is 2022
of course we had this huge uh bull
market they would say so a positive uh
for almost all financial markets going
up
people feeling richer uh also some some
things like houses coming that are
actually used as as consumable Goods as
well things we actually use getting too
expensive for many people but the
homeowners being really happy right
their their values going up
um or most of them
but this year no everything went in
Reverse uh
except for energy so energy stocks make
sense given everything we've talked
about so far with the economic War
energy War went up gold uh roughly flat
so going back to inflation discussion at
the start of the Year someone like Peter
Schiff says oh we printed too much money
everything's going to go into gold
he was right on inflation that is the
inflation went up quite a bit higher but
gold stay flat even in such a high
inflationary environment so that's
interesting the graph's still going a
little bit down but gold has recently
gone up back a little bit so
um that prediction didn't seem to come
true but he did better than the Bitcoin
Bros which had a terrible year this is
the Bitcoin price
Bitcoin Pros being a mean term to
describe uh people who really really
into Bitcoin religiously uh so sorry
about that but Bitcoin had a terrible
year I coined it the crypto's great
financial crisis because so many crypto
financial institutions went out of
business they all went into debt with
the Assumption of higher asset prices in
2021 they were right they got super rich
and now things have gone into reverse
um so for financial markets for most
people terrible year I would say
winners and losers uh winners energy
stocks if you had what energy stocks you
actually would have made money I also
asked some some other Finance channels
uh Ben Felix uh plain bagel and uh
Patrick Boyle if they what they thought
about this and they basically told me
because I don't invest too much myself
I'm more of an economist
energy stocks are the winners of of this
year for the rest basically everyone's
uh losers even though some lost less and
so they were considered doing this by
then but that doesn't fly with me
uh so everything is a loser but
especially tech tech had a terrible year
Amazon down by a lot uh Google that is
alphabet uh meta from Facebook down by a
lot
uh likely because of uh much lower
advertising prices I read that mobile
games have had a huge impact on this
because everybody was staying home for
the pandemic buying a mobile games uh
mobile games doing lots of
advertisements on Instagram and all that
kind of stuff
YouTube perhaps and now less so so
driving prices down uh hitting also uh
YouTube channels uh advertising Revenue
you can definitely notice uh crypto huge
loser of uh 2022. sorry for all of you
invested in crypto
um
deck as well yeah High interest rates of
course also have a uh in economic theory
have a big role to play here right so uh
interest rates going up that kind of
debt or a bank account becoming more
attractive compared to this risky stocks
that was also a big factor here probably
yes uh what do you think
[Music]
financial markets what grade shall we
give this maybe we should say
um for the Baseline scores one to ten
one is if you had money in FTX that's a
one for you uh probably right
uh 10 if you owned energies no no not a
10 that's not nine if you owned energy
stocks I would say
so what would you say is um
financial markets what is is the score
for financial markets this year
seven
okay that's that's pretty good uh 3.5
from Igor
four seven three
Automotive sector was positive okay I
didn't know that
uh okay makes sense given that uh we had
this huge car shortage still
but yeah it was still positive Tesla is
definitely not but maybe that's more
Tech stock
four four three five three three six
four five two oh man okay so this is not
so this is not a good year huh four four
five one one from Mark so the global
stock market uh all asset markets were
as bad as FTX
now that's that's bearish as they they
would say
uh
okay I'm gonna say actually you know
what I was talking to Patrick ball about
this and he said you know if we look at
most financial markets uh it this is
more of a correction still at the moment
if they don't collapse so much further
because it had this huge increase and
now a correction uh is what he said so
so I'm gonna anchor this at discussion
at five I'm gonna say I would say five
because
uh crypto had a great financial crisis
globally asset prices had a terrible
year
lost money but not a great financial
crisis
uh X-Men doesn't play casino with his
money so did not invest in FTX I would
say five so then we're going to say
um
should I say is it too high then yeah
most people were
startup most people were saying it
should be lower four or five threes like
is the Great
five too high for asset markets this
year that is the question is it too high
so should it be lower
my question to you
let me know what you think is too high
yes
um some contestants
it's always a correction uh
says Royal adomi
crash only crash if it never recovers
um
yeah interestingly you know I always
like to look at the from a macro
perspective at the Japanese stock market
how it performed after uh
20 uh 1990 roughly and you know it took
so long for that to recover which really
was interesting because sort of the
common wisdom is always oh yeah on
average stocks are always going up and
for the US that has been the case uh
at least for 100 years or something but
for Japan maybe it's now at that level
but like it took 30 years or something
to recover which is terrible right
uh
spy is below average
so okay I'm just going to end the ball
quickly so that we can move on
the Seance says it should be a 4.8
I'm going to end it and is it too high
yes uh 55 of people says it's too high
so
I said a five so it's a four nice
markets is a four my plan's running at
four
financial markets
for terrible year for financial markets
so that's that's it uh whoops
let's
look at all the numbers again so this
was the review so we're now nearing the
end of the review section of this live
session measure markets 84 terrible year
real did B6 uh still bad here okay we
want to see a seven at least
uh unemployment and eight
underappreciated hopefully your main
takeaway from this
if you're at the Christmas uh dinner
perhaps or some other dinner with
friends or you're at a party hopefully a
New Year's party
actually you know if the reading gloomy
got the economy talk about unemployment
better than most people think
inflation's still five inflation was the
big bad bad Betty this year
ruined the party
all right uh that's so on average what's
it on average I'm gonna get in trouble
not so excited this kind of stuff I need
to give them weight anyway
I would say on average and this is not a
properly weighted average that's a six
the global economy no let's put it at
5.5 because inflation was really
terrible
that is not a not a good year as most of
you agreed to
and um
yeah that sucks
so
that is the main part of this video out
of the way so we've looked at the the
main stories of 2022 we've reviewed the
year on these macroeconomic indicators
and now let's do a q a if you want to
stick around stick around otherwise
feel free to leave but this is an open q
a now
and then I would just only have happy
holidays wish left I'm gonna turn the
camera
to me
uh hello everybody let's shoot me some
questions
okay Kaku says too many papers too few
glasses of dry Scotch yes I have a glass
of tea
try and set a good example dry Scotch
it's been a while since I've enjoyed a
good glass of dry Scotch maybe try it
again this one time I actually got a bit
a bit uh sick from whiskey has been a
while to return here in Belgium I really
enjoyed all of these great Belgian beers
but not too many of them of course but
my goodness that was one of the
highlights of my year
to enjoy a good Belgian beer and peace
on the on the sofa
uh with a good friend talking economics
okay some question okay oh I have a name
that's difficult for me to pronounce but
says what's your opinion on the Dutch
farmer protests so this is also
something that I wanted to
maybe make a video about but didn't get
around to it uh the so for those few not
in the know in the Netherlands there
were actually quite big farmer protests
because
uh well you know the Netherlands
basically wants to get rid of some of
its farmers
which is credited to to some people
because you were having this food crisis
to do throughout the year
and so many people were also saying like
a uh uh this crazy in the food crisis
but let's put a bit of nuance here this
was all about not CO2 but uh uh stick
stuff uh which is uh with you for which
I forgot the English name at the moment
so maybe someone is in the chat will
have you out nitrogen anyway which is
bad for nature areas and there were too
many and it was all about meat and milk
Farmers so it was about mostly about
animals so the argument there I I didn't
find so strong like uh we need food no
we basically mostly need plant-based
food in a food crisis uh sorry so that
that was not a big argument but uh one
part about this which I think is
underappreciated is that
the Dutch government uh you know didn't
communicate about this properly they
were forced to to do this uh in court by
environmental activists uh who and you
know for understandable reasons but then
a lot of these Farmers built like
farming is a hard business and you
invest a ton of money it's very slim
margins and uh you you you you then from
in a poorly proper in a poorly
communicated way get told like hey
you've invested for all these years uh
in your business uh and you you're not
you don't have so much income even
though a farmer is wealthy they often
have a lot of debt it's not not like
they have access to that wealth per se
immediately and it's a way of life and
now uh yeah it's uh you have to stop so
I I can understand why they were very
angry let's put it like that
for for a more informed opinion I would
have to do a full video I would have to
do more research because I don't these
are very touchy subjects
I want to do them Justice
um
yeah um so I'm not completely I don't
have a full opinion on it but I can
understand at least why they were angry
I think the communication there and the
planning was really bad by the Dutch
government
um of course some of these protests also
got out of hand and
were not always conducted in a classy
manner
trying to stay a little bit diplomatic
to avoid any
yeah no I just shouldn't uh shouldn't
have a super strong I typically try to
not have a super strong opinion on stuff
that I didn't research too well
okay
um yeah so this is what kakusa's farmers
are wealth in essence very poor
financially
um in income right
uh okay any more questions
[Music]
um
I would look for China for next year
it depends on the government action so
it really depends on what they will do
um how much stimulus they will give
so far they've given the impression that
they don't want to completely re-inflate
the bubble and they've given the
impression that they cannot
do the structural reforms needed
structure reforms a very vague term
often used in economics to mean all
sorts of sometimes very controversial
things but what I mean here is that they
have this economy that's built to build
build to build build to build all of
these huge Flats
roads trains houses that was very useful
at the start not so useful anymore
um and it's and and then it's very much
export based so investment based and
expert based is what economists call
that typically
Chinese leaders know this they want to
shift towards more consumption based
economy
more also more high high tech more
service but so far it seems like they
don't have the the will to actually do
measures that
really do that so they say they're going
to do it but so far they haven't really
done that and they always reverse back
to re-inflating the property bubble
further so my Outlook and then they have
this huge demographic issue that
um yeah as a result of the one child
policy that there are many you know the
population is seemingly shrinking
there's I've also read some indications
that the population statistics are not
fully reliable so that maybe already
shrinking uh so I still think the Japan
scenario is the most likely
big stagnation and um
at a lower level uh than Japan
which is important for the people in
China which is not good news
um
but
um yeah maybe they know that this is a
problem so maybe they will do the right
policies but then they also seemingly
are getting more authoritarian
and then you know as we've now seen in
Russia that you know slowly if you
surround yourself with only people that
tell you what you want to hear maybe not
great for Governors governance and their
right policies in the long run
the macroeconomy is super tricky huge
huge system uh very difficult to run
properly on your own as a strong person
strong man is what they would say
so I'm not super optimistic I think it
will stagnate further maybe have
maybe even decline a little bit
all right
sorry if I Butch the pronunciation again
is in this decade for growth uh yeah
I've seen quite positive uh you know
numbers are positive more and more
positive
um
uh articles from people that I follow
but uh I need to do more research on
this I don't know yet
enough about the Indian economy really
should uh should do a deep dive
cautiously optimistic
um okay let's see um
it's a question obviously by Michael so
is there more money created by Banks the
money printed by central banks how much
impact do you think money printing has
on inflation compared to overall money
creation
uh yeah so that that's really tricky
question because money printing I it's
all it's not not always clear what
people mean by it how I interpret that
is create money
by Central Bank or
maybe even if maybe even if private
Banks created but the government is it
comes from the government
and it has to end up in the hands of the
people is I what I would say is money
predict because they have to do it to
pay their bills and then it would be
inflationary if it's not used to grow
the economy
that that makes sense right so uh that
happens from time to time it happened in
Sri Lanka and some of these
hyperinflation countries it happens
uh during covert pandemic it actually
happened a little bit in advanced
economies as well
arguably even the the huge fiscal
spending uh during covert pandemic was I
would say that is money printing is
closest to money printing much more
money printing than quantitative easing
is
because you know even if they don't do
it through the
Central Bank they do it through Banks
Banks create money to facilitate to to
lend to the government
that's very close to money printing
right
um how inflationary will it be well it
depends I think if you're in inside a
lockdown situation where you're
capacity to make stuff is severely
constrained yeah it makes sense that it
contributes to inflation
if you do it in a way that grows the
economy it's not inflationary but that's
very difficult and maybe it takes time
so I can understand it's on average
inflationary so yes proper money
printing I would yeah it's necessary to
grow an economy sometimes
it is still probably slightly
inflationary
but it's very rare in advanced economies
rarely sort of what
people like Ray dalio talk about in this
very simple terms money printing oh they
just
uh oh they're going to print money and
then they're going to devalue their
currency how they used to do it in uh in
in the 17th century we just don't live
in an economy anymore because most
money that central banks create is only
used as interbank money between Banks
so you need the private sector then to
follow and it doesn't always happen
okay Daniel coxeel says here any
thoughts on demographic change happening
around the world a lot of baby boomers
approaching uh retirement age especially
in Europe which will affect the economy
yes I think you already saw this in the
US uh there the unemployment rate is uh
fairly low
and it's shot but more interestingly the
labor participation rate so how many
people of your population are in the
labor force really dropped uh and what I
read about this mostly is that a lot of
these baby boomer Generations or a big
generational wave
I thought you know what yeah with this
covert wave I'm just gonna quit early
and so
there's a theory by professor goodheart
and an Indian Economist whose name I
just forgot what
I mentioned in my inflation video
[Music]
um
their theory is that this will be
inflationary because you have this
production in labor force
and this aging generation is going to
spend spend there this just the money
they saved so that if that's true
it should
um
see like pressure on asset price to go
down further and inflationary pressure
um and that but that might also be good
for low that we have lower unemployment
for longer now if that is true
I think it's uh it's a convincing
hypothesis we haven't seen it in Japan
yet but
they maybe outsourced a lot of of that
work is what these professors are saying
yeah uh it's a convincing hypothesis but
let's uh I'll need to dive more into the
demographic stuff a little bit to be to
be honest it's not my specialty
Financial economics more where I came
from uh but uh you know I always do most
of my research for for all of these
videos
um
okay Gary says do you think AI can help
the global economy you know I started
using this chatbot uh chat GPT to help
me sort of rewrite uh one or two
paragraphs
I was mildly impressed uh the the the
writing was good
but but uh it clearly didn't know what
it was talking about very well so it was
only mildly useful but that being said
I've seen some of these AIS do
animations and so it I think it
definitely contributes to this process
of what Economist schumpeter calls
creative destruction
which is all about sort of the economy
sort of getting rid of the old
Industries and building new ones and
then thereby growing the economy because
as a whole you become more productive
and so as a whole you have more stuff
right and this is also why I would say
GDP could potentially grow even if we
have finite resources
and the AI Revolution is uh is is
definitely one of the coolest things
I've seen so far unexpected because I
thought after
of the deep learning stuff uh with uh
them defeating go and doing really cool
stuff in games like Starcraft uh but
then I saw it like
stole out a little bit but now to see it
continuing this this innovative
uh I can definitely see it contributing
to economic growth for sure yeah very uh
cool development
um all right
what are Mark what are your thoughts on
the depth to GTP ratio uh it's still
high
but especially in country like China but
maybe if inflation ends up maybe coming
down but not going back to deflation so
we have permanently higher prices
because Energy prices and food were
maybe the ones that contributed most
this year but wages I don't believe in
this wage price spiral that it should
spiral out of control but wages are
likely going to catch up and that would
contribute to inflation for longer and
also you can see it now already here in
coffee shops that you know they're
charging higher prices because of higher
entity prices which makes total sense
because it's a huge input cost so it
makes sense that inflation is going to
be broader
now that would contribute to more
inflation next year but would mean that
the debt to that is more manageable
so the adapt to normal GDP ratio of
course wouldn't really matter but adapt
to real GDP ratio
would go down uh because of this that
could be
so okay uh Gaspard says can you make a
video looking at economic and macro
impacts of strikes
um
so I do have to take into account a
little bit also what people are looking
for and I haven't seen too many demand
for that but like that
but what I try to do now often is if
there is an economic case or
I try to put some theory in in that con
like country analysis for example so
maybe
if something happened where we see a lot
of strikes I can put I can tie it into
that because it is an interesting
subject
all right
um okay so shung says uh if I pronounce
correctly how should most people store
money during a recession uh
ooh crypto getting kidding uh have a
look at some um I think plain bagel made
a video about this he's a professional
investor that's honest in my opinion
check that out that's a better Source
than me at the moment for this
all right so uh I I don't see so many
questions uh coming anymore and I think
this has been a good review session
and with that being said thank you so
much all of you for uh joining me here
reviewing the global economy in 2020 at
2022 thanks so much for supporting the
money micro Channel by watching and by
subscribing and some of you also by
being patrons or members really helps me
out a lot my plan for next year is to
try and release my my goal would be two
videos per month uh but it's very tricky
for me and then one live stream that's
what I hope
but uh around March
uh that's really nice I likely am going
to be a father so it could be that
you're gonna be missing me for a month
or something or maybe longer depending
on how it goes so I'm really looking
forward to 2023 for that reason but I'm
going to try to
become more consistent this is my goal
two videos per month and one interview
and then I've been working on a course
monetary economics I want to make this
subject
more approachable so in the money micro
style with nice examples and as little
jargon as possible and that should come
out next year I've been working with two
interns this year that have helped make
a lot more possible than otherwise would
have been possible Oscar and Carla thank
you so much for helping me out this year
and thank you Hugo for helping me out
with the animations
so much and thank you all for the
congratulation messages I'm uh super
happy about this as well
so looking forward to 2023 I hope the
economy will get a better score at the
end of 2023
and with that being said
thank you all so much hope you have a
great holidays uh and oh new video in
two days about turkey economy last video
of uh he okay Aragon really did some
interesting moves there some
geopolitical moves to stabilize the
currency doesn't happen so much uh super
interesting video go check it out and
enjoy your holidays see you next year